Guide to the D.W. Hering Papers MC 74
New York University Archives
D.W. Hering Papers
1889-1939
MC 74
New York University Archives
1.0 linear feet
Daniel Webster Hering's career at New York University spanned 40 years. As a professor, dean, or curator he was affiliated with the University from 1885 until his death in 1938.
Provenance
The collection was originally accessioned by Theodore Francis Jones, a University professor and director of the library, circa 1932. At that time, Jones was compiling a centennial history of the University (New York University: 1832-1932). The D.W. Hering Papers became part of the historical collection that Jones housed in the "treasure room" at the University Heights campus. With the sale of that campus in 1973, the collection was transferred to the New York University Archives.
Separated Materials
No materials have been deaccessioned or separated.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection has no access restrictions.
Additionally, New York University has determined that all digitized works presented as part of the D.W. Hering Papers Finding Aid are in the public domain. The images available on this website may be freely reproduced, distributed and transmitted by anyone for any purpose, commercial or non-commercial.
Biography
Daniel Webster Hering was born near Smithburg, Maryland, on March 23, 1850, and died in New York City on March 24, 1938. A mathematical prodigy, he obtained a Maryland teaching certificate at the age of 11. Hering earned baccalaureate and graduate degrees in civil engineering from Yale University. After working as a railroad civil engineer, Dr. Hering turned to teaching. He taught at Western Maryland College and Western University (now the University of Pittsburgh) before coming to New York University.
In 1885, he was appointed professor of physics at NYU. His tenure at the University was synonymous with the development of the College of Engineering. Among his noteworthy scientific endeavors was early work in Roentgen X-rays. He took what may be the first radiograph of an entire human body.
Hering became Dean of the Graduate School in 1902 and served in that post until his retirement in 1916. In 1926, however, the University Council appointed him curator of the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches, which was then housed at the University. He devoted much energy and enthusiasm to that collection during his final years.
Mathematician, physicist, engineer, educator, and author, Hering lived a long life characterized by accomplishment. His life also spanned a remarkable period of American history. Born before the Civil War, he lived almost to the outbreak of World War II.
Additional biographical information on D.W. Hering is contained in his own memoir and in a biographical sketch by two of his colleagues. Both items are part of this collection.
Related Materials
See the James Arthur Clock Collection (RG 42.1) for further information on Hering's tenure as its curator from 1926-1938.
Scope and Content
The collection measures one linear foot and is composed almost exclusively of writings and photographs by Hering.
Bound volumes in the collection gather together clippings and reprints of Hering's articles, his typewritten annals of the College of Engineering, and biographical essays on New York University professors. Other materials include mimeographed brochures on the James Arthur Collection of Timepieces, a travel book (in bound typescript), and his unbound memoirs (also in typescript). The memoirs and travel book are profusely illustrated with original photographs, including images documenting his work in Roentgenology. Dr. Hering's writings reflect his wide range of interests, from physics to football, and from travel to timepieces.
Among the other items in the collection is a brief biographical essay on Hering, written by his colleagues I.F. Berg and T.F. Jones.
The collection retains its original order except for some preliminary sleeving of photographs and foldering of unbound typescripts. With one or two exceptions, the collection's materials are in good condition.
There are significant gaps in the collection. Prominent among them are several additional travel books, the composition of which Hering records in his memoirs, and his few published scientific volumes. The collection also contains almost no correspondence.
- Series I, 1889-1939
  - Memoirs, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memoirs, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoirs, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autobiography, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitation, letter, and speech, 1896, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical sketch, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tour of England, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, passenger lists, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Relative and Absolute Values of Electrical Units, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1889-1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Biographies, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annals of the Department of Engineering, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - James Arthur Collection of Timepieces, 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minor writings, 1927-1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Late and posthumous publications, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)